<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Twilight and Shadow</title><description>Twilight and Shadow</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 09:09:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>The gypsies of the High Country</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The month of May means it's &lt;a href="http://twalk.cutc.org.nz/"&gt;TWALK&lt;/a&gt; time - basically the best event of the year right? I mean, what's not to love about dressing up and running round the hillsides for 24 hours? Because we are a disorganised bunch, L just entered a group of us and gave us a team name, The Gypsies. We thought it seemed like a pretty good theme although I'm not sure the boys were convinced until they realised that all gypsies need, a caravan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-T9eatx9jg38/VXvBXyq0dQI/AAAAAAAAGig/8zUfB0cC-jU/s640/twalk-prep.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Having a bit of a caravan construction party!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some late nights and early mornings at our house constructing the magnificent speciman. In fact, one morning I woke up about 6am to the sound of the sewing machine running! Miraculously it was finally complete late on the Thursday night so we had Friday night to do the rest of the prep. M really got into the sewing thing, with the 2 of us constructing some fairly hilarious trousers for the occasion as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we arrived at the university carpark we had to put our caravan together to parade our hard work around the carpark for a couple of laps before deconstructing it again to fit on the bus. So much entertainment! We even had a little speaker 'blasting out' gypsy music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xBh0sPrg4j4/VWbTZTO3eAI/AAAAAAAAGgo/aCjkTSt0IX4/s640/caravan.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;The Gypsies and our caravan at Lake Pearson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-0tI-dJ_XMCA/VXvA4f1qtPI/AAAAAAAAGiQ/tqWtwR5HqA0/s640/twalk-start.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Checking out the course with M and L.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about TWALK is not knowing where you are going. There was much tension amongst the team about how 'caravan-friendly' it was going to be! We kept driving further and further into the high country and ended up stopping by Lake Pearson which got as all excited. It was also ridiculously windy which made us not so excited. Fortunately we only had to get the caravan round the first leg but even that was a struggle despite the boys carting it round easier routes for the second half. It sure slowed us all down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-jo83rvSTCyo/VXvCGDpcoiI/AAAAAAAAGis/CpzSUdqCz-I/s640/twalkytwalk.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;The boys and their caravan on Leg 1. It's starting to fall apart on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so glad to reach the hashhouse at Craigieburn Station, an awesome location. The next couple of legs all went okay apart from a freezing cold and wet section on leg 2 at the top of a mountain after the sun went down but that's just all part of the fun right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-wjKWumx_zUc/VWbTZQ9AipI/AAAAAAAAGgk/rTaP2DcsDM0/s800/twalk-leg2.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Leg 2, galloping through the tussock above the Waimakariri River. Sorry Jamie, I stole your photo because it's awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leg 4 however, there are just no words to describe quite how awful and ridiculous this leg was. Not only were the controls mostly insanely difficult/impossible to find but from #4 the terrain became insane. Getting down the hillside to the river I don't think my feet ever touched the ground as I attempted to bash down through the scrub. Then it was a case of either bashing through gorse or wading deep in a freezing cold river...for what felt like hours! Then to get back up the bank again you found yourself grabbing hold of matagouri to stop you sliding back down again. I think I'm still extracting splinters to this day! Add in some more steep climbs only to not find the controls and you get the idea. We got back to the hash house with less than an hour left which meant only about 26 minutes or something for a brief dash round a couple of controls on leg 5 (there is a mandatory standdown of half an hour between each leg).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-_TQLW48QnIU/VXvA6BwIjZI/AAAAAAAAGiY/pzMbXTqWtco/s500/delapidated-caravan.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Our poor caravan looking a little worse for wear outside the Woolshed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up coming second after coming in from the first leg quite a way behind the fast teams but we did win the glorious prize of best costume which we were pretty stoked about. Next year will be the 50th event which is pretty exciting! But I really hope we don't have to carry round a ridiculously large and awkward prop again!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/gypsies-of-the-high-country/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a17662c3-3e78-430f-8ebc-de82f8d5a92f</guid><category>rogaine</category><category>life</category><category>adventures</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2015 05:45:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>When it rains it pours</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Anzac weekend (yay for now having Mondayised public holidays!) we took the Friday off to head down to Te Anau again, this time so I could "race" the &lt;a href="http://goodtimesevents.net/?event=routburn"&gt;Routeburn Classic&lt;/a&gt; on the Saturday. We got there in the afternoon and basked in the sunshine...from within our cabin where it was warm and there was a bed to do our basking on. Unfortunately though, the sunny weather was not to hold...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a pretty early start the next morning, with the bus heading to the startline leaving at 6am, getting us to the Divide in time for an 8am start. Lots of us were getting into the spirit by wearing our heros masks from the race pack which turned out to be a cool edition since it helped kept my head warm!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it was raining and cold at the start and continued to be raining and cold for the whole race but the Routeburn is pretty darn spectacular all the same. Running along the tops after the climb up from Mackenzie Hut was tough going though as the rain was horizontal and the wind was pretty strong. I kept getting water in my contacts which blurred my vision - not good when the track drops off steeply next to you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-FirIERxCnHY/VWbXUc3qFuI/AAAAAAAAGg8/R_zAx5TKyeo/s500/routeburnrace.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Arriving at the Routeburn Falls hut. Yep, I'm still wearing my heros mask - it helped keep my head warm!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was a super fun race and especially exciting to have M cheering me on at the Routeburn Falls hut. Yay! Unfortunately he got a bit sore and tired on the way back and I bet him to the finish which was an impressive feat since I was going at snail pace. Not to worry though since there were lots of people to cheer me on anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-5ybA1iy-5Oo/VWbW2pmNJRI/AAAAAAAAGg0/KdSk7s2pVm0/s640/myMedia.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;The finishline, heros style. There was even a crash mat for us all to 'fly' onto. Good times!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pretty happy with my time since I really just wanted to get under 4 hours 30 but I can't say I pushed very hard so I might have to come back another year and attempt a sub 4. Actually pushing myself would probably help, as well as better weather conditions! It was fun though! Such a cool atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, after a nice long sleepin, we ventured out to the Milford Sound into the wild weather for a cruise. If only we could take good photos because the ones below make it look just wet and dreary. In fact the rain meant heaps more waterfalls (and I LOVE waterfalls) and this really spectacular atmosphere. I would love to come back on a rare day when it's sunny as you'd get a sense of the scale of things. The mountains quite literally rise straight out of the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Id1ntNHk_og/VWbZ73qFujI/AAAAAAAAGhQ/xrRlolTY2MA/s640/milford.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's how it looks when it's sunny! We've been working on this puzzle during the increasingly colder and darker nights!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-EGclW_2sSQM/VWbZ7bd9TJI/AAAAAAAAGhM/kwcKenThjEU/s640/puzzle.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that does surprise me is how many tourists we saw down here without real jackets. Seriously, if you are planning on visiting New Zealand, especially the West Coast or Fiordland, ummm, bring a decent raincoat no matter the season. You will almost certainly get wet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that's enough chatter for now. So much is getting banked up. I even have delicious food to talk about, not to mention the gypsy caravan...&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/when-it-rains-it-pours/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">17f18d1a-7733-4d57-9a8b-e1286647f2d8</guid><category>running</category><category>offroad</category><category>life</category><category>adventures</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 09:39:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Horrible runs and magic runs</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Before we embark on the final long weekend before we get plunged into the depths of winter (sigh) I better get cracking and get myself up to date! It's been exhausting over the last couple of months. It seems crazy/weird but the winter period always seems to be the main event season. At least it keeps you moving through the dark months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So last time I wrote, M and I had just raced Le Race and then I'd just flown home from a quick trip up to Auckland to run a half marathon across Rangitoto and Motutapu because, well, it seemed like a good excuse to visit my parents! Like I said on that &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/le-windy-hilly-exhausting-rewarding-race/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I really don't recommend a tough off-road half marathon the weekend after going hard in an even tougher 100km bike race! I suspect I haven't learnt my lesson though...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've raced &lt;a href="http://thedual.co.nz/"&gt;The Dual&lt;/a&gt; half marathon &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/run_run_as_fast_as_you_can_/"&gt;twice&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/the_dual_half_marathon/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, several years ago and was kind of keen to get a PB but I hadn't had the best buildup with some niggly foot issues and spending all summer riding a bike instead of running. I don't run in the same way I used to back then either, with runs these days usually heading straight up into the Port Hills and then back down again and I'd forgotten how much 'flat' running there was on this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-It5-XbAdUYk/VWbB3OyfTMI/AAAAAAAAGf4/YYAX0QuQifs/s640/DUAL2015_029139.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Basically hitting the wall super badly heading over the top of Motutapu for the final time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was really not my day. I've forgotten how horribly humid Auckland can be and this sure was one of those days. Pretty much the moment the gun went off I felt awful, just super dizzy and my vision kept blacking out. Just shows how sleep-deprived I'd managed to get in the build up. Somehow, despite this, I made it up and over Motutapu and Rangitoto to the wharf in fairly good time (I think it was roughly an hour to that point which is around the 11km mark and with a fair amount of the climb done). I even managed the technical singletrack round the edge of Rangitoto okay but the dizziness was getting pretty bad and my 'cycling legs' (i.e. thighs feeling like blocks of wood) were really kicking in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I'd made good time but the final climb over Motutapu back to the finish, well, I just felt so ill so powerwalked most of the final 4km. It was awful! Then, with the finish in sight, I got confused and tried to go through a fence instead of following everyone else (totally my orienteering background coming into play here!). My parents had taken the ferry over to see me finish so I had a cheer squad at the finish which was awesome but I was so gladd to finish. 7 seconds slower than my best which sucked since I lost that trying to cross the stupid fence! But pretty impressive since I walked most of the final 4km! Unfortunately though the race really took its toll on my body and I was horribly sick on the ferry trip home and didn't really recover for another week. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then it was Easter...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M was racing the Tour de Lakes so I was there as support crew (and doing it badly!) and to check out either end of the Routeburn as I was entered to race it 3 weeks later and racing isn't exactly the best way to enjoy what I'd heard was one of the most scenic tramping tracks around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing my best not to screw up my support crew role on Friday and Saturday I had a super early start on Sunday to drive the long road out from Manapouri to the Divide where I planned to run the track out to Lake MacKenzie and back (about 12km one way). In an ideal world I'd have gone further but I was supposed to get back to Five Rivers in time to meet M after his afternoon race and it was at least a 2 hour drive (so much driving...sigh).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-CqUR9fKSM5M/VWbKyowTaGI/AAAAAAAAGgI/h2OQ1nIYCX0/s640/routeburn1.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I just don't have the words to describe that morning. From the moment you set foot on the track it is so incredibly beautiful. The bush was amazing (but beech forest is always beautiful), especially with the early morning sun casting thin rays of light through the trees. Then you reach Earnslaw falls and I'm a definite sucker for a waterfall so I hung out there for awhile (and again on the way back when the water hitting the pool at the bottom was creating a rainbow!). Then you cruise along the side where you get some stunning views of surround mountains before dropping sharply down to Lake Mackenzie where I hung out for a while, wishing I could head up on to the tops as the weather was so perfect. After a sandwich and a laze in the sun it was back again. Quite possibly my favourite run ever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday morning M woke up feeling sick so wasn't able to race but fortunately he was happy enough to sleep in the car whilst I headed out on the track from the Routeburn Shelter end this time. The weather wasn't quite so good but most of this side of the track is in bush and quite low. I cruised along the flats then up the hill to the Routeburn Falls just in time for the weather to pack in which defintely made it pretty atmospheric! I cruised along the tops for a little while but it was getting pretty wet and cold so I figured it was time to head down again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-YGQxwgVe_cI/VWbSTZ4WEhI/AAAAAAAAGgY/Sy91ncMoihk/s640/routeburn2.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the day before, I met plenty of people all keen to chat and everyone was finding the experience as magical as I was. It helped to remind me just what an incredible country I live in. And by now I was super excited about the race in 3 weeks time (and also had learnt that trying to run over swing bridges is not fun).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you wanted to see some actual nice footage of the Routeburn rather than just my shocking photos, check out &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/hIKSJYuyZ10"&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; or, just actually go and do it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up...wild Southland weather and the Gypsy Caravan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/horrible-runs-and-magic-runs/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">201a817a-0a1d-423f-a504-70e6c39b9eff</guid><category>running</category><category>offroad</category><category>life</category><category>adventures</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 08:34:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Le (windy, hilly, exhausting, rewarding) Race</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello! So sore, so tired. Don't go doing a half marathon just a week after giving it your all doing a 100km cycling race! But I'm getting ahead of myself (this is what happens when you get behind in posting!)...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since moving to Christchurch (nearly 4 years ago now - time flies!) I had always wanted to do &lt;a href="http://www.lerace.co.nz/"&gt;Le Race&lt;/a&gt;, the 100km road cycling race from Christchurch to Akaroa. 2015 was my chance, with M keen to tackle it on the tandem with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We've been putting in plenty of "training" (i.e. going for the usual fun rides round the Port Hills and the odd adventure further out on the Banks Peninsula). You don't get photos because I'm too busy riding :-P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then on Tuesday nights during daylight savings we can usually be found at the &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Canterbury-Time-Trial-Association/250916344952513?fref=ts"&gt;CTTA&lt;/a&gt; time trials, a 16km there and back time trial along Old Tai Tapu Road. It's tough, especially for those of us who'd rather be riding up a hill than riding on the flat, but fun (well, once you've finished)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-eFqc9ZjcQ8w/VRkEfWrj7sI/AAAAAAAAGbY/3hjBrWKE7V0/s640/_MG_6583.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Giving it all we have at the CTTA time trials. Photo credit: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Christopher-Innes-Photography/307974185897650?fref=ts" target="_blank"&gt;Christopher Innes Photography&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a year there is also the 16km hillclimb time trial from the Blue Duck cafe up to Gebbies Pass then up the Basdrat (M's anagram for what most cyclists normally call it - I'll let you work that one out) then along the tops to just past Kennedy's. It is brutal but we got a new PB this season which was exciting even if it might be partly down to perfect weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously there was a lot of cycling over the summer holidays with our &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/tag/cycle-tour-20142015/"&gt;cycle touring&lt;/a&gt; trip. We'd also been out making sure we were familiar with all parts of the course. Well, M was pretty familiar with it already but the tandem is a different (much heavier!) kettle of fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was still going to be a tough race. Le Race is definitely not a tandem-friendly course, that's for sure (tandems are not the greatest climbers, especially as it gets steeper and Le Race is definitely not a flat race). Unfortunately I'd managed to slip over and injure my back at an afterwork rogaine on the Wednesday and was still in some discomfort so the goal of getting under 3hrs 30 became a goal to finish before midday (4hrs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We positioned ourselves by the 3:30-4:00 sign which did make for a bit of a slow start but once we got going it was pretty cool to be whizzing past everyone along Colombo Street, and still continuing passing riders heading up Dyers which surprised me as I always expected to get dropped on the steep climbs. Once along the tops it started to get pretty misty and cold with the visibility decreasing rapidly. I was glad I wasn't the one steering! Fortunately we emerged out of the mist before heading down the Basdrat (and the dreaded cattlestops) to Gebbies. We hit the flat at high speed and in good time which was exciting! Plus M's parents were there cheering us on! And then the real hard work began...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a bunch of about 6 of us to start I think which took a while to get itself organised while we spent a lot of time out the front in the super strong easterly wind. Finally the bunch got working and that was quite exciting, having never ridden in a bunch before. Our bunch slowly grew as we caught more people and we were slowly closing in on the bunch ahead as we made it to Little River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully expected us to get dropped on the long (long long long!!) climb up to Hilltop but it was quite the opposite with us even overtaking some of the bunch ahead of us. Unfortunately the climbing wasn't so good on my back and the pain was creeping in. But M was still on form and we were flying along once we got to the tops. But then the lack of sleep caught up with him and it was up to me to keep us going! There are so many steep, energy-sapping climbs along the Summit Road after Hilltop and it was really taking it's toll. Add on the wild winds attempting to blow us off the road (in these conditions there are some benefits with being on such a super heavy bike!) and it was fast turning into a bit of a miserable experience! The tops went on and on and by the last couple of climbs I had nothing left in my legs. Thankfully M had recovered a little bit by then otherwise I might have had to get off and walk!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little worried about the descent down Long Bays Road as it is super steep and has quite a few reasonably straight sections meaning we can pick up quite a bit of speed (cornering is another thing tandems aren't so good at) but it was really quite exciting passing people going down Long Bays Rd (and yes, quite terrifying too at that speed!). It was pretty windy on the descent so our weight probably helped us be able to go faster and stay in control compared to the other riders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-HmFu11Y3nE0/VRkDrTGCJ0I/AAAAAAAAGbQ/L7gDhXqluBY/s640/20x30-LERB0357.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;On our way down Long Bays Road and nearly finished - I may look relaxed but let me tell you, I am anything but calm! Photo credit: &lt;a href="https://www.marathon-photos.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Marathon Photos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited to reach the finish. I'm not a natural cyclist and it's taken an awful lot of work to be able to ride a bike at all. After my mountain bike crash a couple of years ago I had struggled a lot with the fear that used to cripple me earlier when I would go riding and the frustration of not being able to ride in the same way that I used to. I am so thankful for M putting up with me (and my occasional screams!) on the tandem.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/le-windy-hilly-exhausting-rewarding-race/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">cd81d89b-a592-46a4-b176-fa4251d1585d</guid><category>road cycling</category><category>tandem cycling</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 09:02:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>And we climb up and up and up</title><description>&lt;p&gt;On Waitangi Weekend (which now feels like a lifetime ago!) M and I decided to head up north to climb &lt;a href="http://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-go/nelson-tasman/places/kahurangi-national-park/things-to-do/tracks/mt-owen-tracks-and-routes/"&gt;Mt Owen&lt;/a&gt;. It was raining when we left home on Thursday night and the rain just got heavier and heavier so once we reached our campsite for the night (Deer Valley just below the Lewis Pass) putting up a tent didn't seem like such a pleasant idea. Plus it was getting pretty late by this point so we ended up sleeping in the car. We woke up to a super cold but beautiful morning. Snow had fallen on the mountains above us and it was pretty magical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-1wFn8FCK_UQ/VP65iyaEuiI/AAAAAAAAGXk/eY_xmKUdnHY/s640/lewis-pass.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived at the start of the track around lunchtime and began the big ascent up to Granity Pass Hut. You climb up and up through steep beech forest for several hours before reaching the tree line. Then you scramble down what's called the staircase which is a rather steep descent back through the bush before walking along a dry riverbed up to the hut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-6_FYxthOyEI/VQ5-WPFBnNI/AAAAAAAAGZ0/k29DntKx_Js/s640/01-mt-owen.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hut was pretty full when we got there but there were still some bunks free. Not long after we'd cooked up some dinner though (&lt;a href="http://www.absolutewilderness.co.nz/product/mushroom-risotto/"&gt;Absolute Wilderness Mushroom Risotto&lt;/a&gt; for the win!) more people arrived! Clearly it was the place to be!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning dawned truly spectacular - a perfect day for climbing Mt Owen. I've been here before, many years ago (at the start of the millennium  in fact!) but we never actually climbed to the summit so I was pretty excited. It's a fairly easy track to the tarns at the base of the mountain then some rock scrambling which freaked me out (think deep crevasses, but in rock form - there is a huge cave network underneath the mountain) and then the final steep climb up to the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-PXPe2JJBoos/VP65kn4jEgI/AAAAAAAAGXw/Fa3UKYEn8C8/s550/mt-owen-awesome-shot.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-8oazFp4V70I/VQ5-WAa9SKI/AAAAAAAAGZ4/xrpoHXZC33U/s640/02-mt-owen.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was still a bit of snow on the top but nothing too serious and the view was just amazing. For any of you Lord of the Rings fans out there, Mt Owen was the location for Dimrill Dale when the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=59BHNYpKx2A"&gt;fellowship emerge from the Mines of Moria&lt;/a&gt;. It really does look exactly as it does in the movie. Pretty cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-supxSp158PM/VP65lOpvV7I/AAAAAAAAGX0/zFHA99Stkhc/s640/mt-owen-awesome-shot-2.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we got back down to the hut we decided to pitch our tent under a rock outcrop in the valley nearby. It was an awesome spot for such a calm, clear night. I couldn't resist running back up to the tarns in the afternoon after we'd set up camp for the night. It is just too spectacular a location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-1YZPT4TlzoI/VQ5-WN_HwEI/AAAAAAAAGZ8/IqLKkUN8xlQ/s640/03-mt-owen.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a bit of a long drive back to Christchurch so we got started pretty early the next morning in more glorious sunshine. I really didn't want to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-1wkV9pikdFQ/VQ5_covePPI/AAAAAAAAGaU/JcoFlVxT0jQ/s640/04-mt-owen.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xgc6LK223tU/VQ5_c1EmZGI/AAAAAAAAGaY/qjSvPfxrvDk/s640/05-mt-owen.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The descent back to the car was pretty long and painful on the knees. I much prefer going uphill! Still, at least you had a glorious view over the mountains of the Kahurangi National Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to come back again, hopefully soon. Perhaps next time we could climb up from the other side. I have lived in this country all my life but it still amazes me just how beautiful it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and one more picture just because I miss M's awesome beard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-TFIDuaH2IUY/VQ5_cwK4F6I/AAAAAAAAGac/Oh46cJGUruY/s640/06-mt-owen.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/untitled-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">75350c07-461b-41be-9e2d-5ac7707ff11d</guid><category>tramping</category><category>life</category><category>adventures</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 09:02:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lazy days of summer</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Since returning from our cycling trip we've been enjoying the beautiful summer weather. I don't remember such a spectular summer in a long time! We clearly weren't sick of biking since 2 days after getting home we were back up in the hills with a couple of friends checking out the newly re-opened road (well, opened to bikes and pedestrians which is awesome!) around Mt Pleasant. Super exciting! It's a bit bumpy for speedy road cycling but it's now officially open and that's the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-K_FKyHnXVTQ/VP65b_FQ4OI/AAAAAAAAGXE/__44CbSpLZA/s640/mt-pleasant-ride.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also a solo excursion up to Trig M from the bottom of Porters Pass while M and his friend were riding the Darfield to Arthur's Pass race. SO hot! One day it would be cool to take the mountain bikes up here although a bit of a grunt. It was hard enough work running/shuffling! From the trig you have a glorious view over Lake Lyndon and towards Craigieburn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-dadcPy6dumY/VP65dm1b3sI/AAAAAAAAGXM/bbk-pN8yTV4/s640/trig-m.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following day, we headed up towards Mt Aicken, getting most of the way up before deciding to turn back 'cause I wasn't having the best of days up there in amongst all the rock (it is pretty cool how much the vegetation changes from various different beech to scrub to tussock to nothing but rock and scree). The views were spectacular though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ZHXd7veDMoQ/VP65ekFVzYI/AAAAAAAAGXU/ffqG2GZRZSY/s640/arthurs-pass.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother also came down to visit for a little while in the summer for some wind surfing. We took him to Okains Bay for a night and camped amongst the trees. Awesome! Then, after spending the morning splashing around in the water and attempting to steer the paddleboard against the current (way too much hard work for very little progress!) we headed to Akaroa for delicious sorbet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/--CJpRHYJSXE/VP65g_Yel2I/AAAAAAAAGXc/G8HPWmAC7Ks/s640/okains-bay.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an excursion to Auckland and our beach house for my lovely cousin's wedding somewhere sandwiched between but I don't have any photos of that! It was awesome though! Amongst all this we've been getting in our training for Le Race which is coming up in a week and a half and I've been trying (and slowly succeeding) to get back into running in time for a couple of races coming up. After all the riding we've been doing this summer though it's been hard work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also went on an exciting adventure to Mt Owen for Waitangi weekend but that's a story for next time!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/lazy-days-of-summer/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">3d5d5e83-c763-4ed4-b7d1-4ee10c00d510</guid><category>running</category><category>tramping</category><category>life</category><category>road cycling</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><category>family</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 09:15:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We all scream for pizza</title><description>&lt;p&gt;If you're hungry and craving pizza you can now get vegan cheese on your pizzas at &lt;a href="http://hellpizza.com/nz/"&gt;Hell&lt;/a&gt;! Well, I'm sure every vegan in New Zealand already knows this but hey, you never know...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-XSzVyEINnI4/VPAxeYsBKZI/AAAAAAAAGRc/nO7ZDmUU0uo/s640/hell-pizza.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about it? The cheese is made in New Zealand by Alice and co from &lt;a href="http://www.angelfood.co.nz/"&gt;Angel Food&lt;/a&gt; (and I can buy it at my local supermarket which is pretty exciting if you ask me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many more adventures to tell from our summer but in the mean time you should follow the &lt;a href="http://godzoneadventure.com/"&gt;Godzone Adventure Race&lt;/a&gt; which many of our friends are about to start tomorrow morning. Exciting times (you'd be surprised just how exciting it is to watch the little trackers move around the screen)!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/untitled/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6d0ec0b1-71f1-49e4-8bcb-6e9f27628698</guid><category>food</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2015 09:06:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>In which the big green monster finally makes it home: Part Five</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I always knew that the homeward leg was going to be a bit tough. For a start, I didn't want to go home...I wanted to keep on biking all day, every day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to hang around and laze in the sun (well, actually the shade as the sun was too hot) most of the day in Tekapo (after a morning run up round Mt John to take in the amazing scenery) before riding the short distance to Fairlie in the late afternoon. In retrospect we perhaps left it a bit too late in the afternoon as the wind had picked up a lot and it felt a bit like riding backwards! The wind died down a little bit over Burkes Pass but it sure got colder!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-To5aXYIuB68/VNh4tFLOqAI/AAAAAAAAGOc/SnFNCW93294/s640/19-day11scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Burkes Pass. Need petrol?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a glorious cabin at Fairlie and managed to do a mountain of washing and eat a mountain of hot chips. Yummy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day we decided we didn't want to take the long route round to Geraldine which that meant we were going to be riding on a fairly busy bit of highway so an early start was required to beat the traffic. Worked pretty well but it sure was a cold start! I was feeling pretty cheerful especially when I got to go to the chocolate shop and buy copious amounts of fresh raspberries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a super long stop at Geraldine we headed off to &lt;a href="http://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-visit/canterbury/mid-and-south-canterbury/peel-forest-park/"&gt;Peel Forest&lt;/a&gt; and the lovely DOC campground there. Unfortunately it was still pretty drizzly which is never fun for putting up tents. There are some lovely walks through the bush here...we only explored a fraction of them. I shall have to come back another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-j43_sen_GPc/VNh4tErcjxI/AAAAAAAAGOk/tNfykExdDU4/s640/20-day12scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Making friends with the trees in Peel Forest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day was again rather drizzly and cold in the morning and was fairly uneventful apart from meeting a few cycle tourists all heading the other direction (it must have been because it was drizzling right?) and getting brain freeze from ice blocks in Mount Somers. I'm not sure why, on all the days when it was super hot, we never got ice creams or ice blocks and yet on such a cold day we did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-FT5kgsUE8gQ/VNh4tOBq3rI/AAAAAAAAGOg/tgIB385v8JY/s640/21-day13scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Clockwise from top left:The General Store at Mount Somers, Moas!!, enjoying the view at Rakaia Gorge, our campsite at Rakaia gorge. What you can't see is the amazing view over the river it had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole way to the Rakaia Gorge until the final descent felt like one long gradual climb, sucking all the life out of my legs! But it is such a lovely &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Rakaia-Gorge-Camping-Ground/251779948174093"&gt;campsite&lt;/a&gt; to stay at. The last time I was here was for Spring Challenge a few years back after we'd rafted down the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more day to go and then we'd be home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-end0M_BXpfI/VNh4uAQdXLI/AAAAAAAAGOw/sLLKp_eLKeY/s640/22-day14scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Left: desperately trying to get all my gear into my pannier one last time. Right: posing whilst overlooking the Rakaia river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up the next morning to thick mist, barely able to see more than a few metres ahead of us. Whilst cooking breakfast though it slowly started to burn off and blue sky was peeking through. The ride out of the gorge is a really nice little climb then it was long, straight, flat roads for ages. M was in semi time trial mode from the 22km to Hororata sign right the way into the town which was amusing but we made it in 41 minutes so he was happy and I was impressed as the wind was pretty cruel. We were making excellent time and were both feeling pretty good so we pushed on to Tai Tapu for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-_1Xo0guKg2w/VNh4utVFBQI/AAAAAAAAGO0/9OiYXIXg4g8/s640/23-day14scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Feasting at &lt;a href="http://www.thestoretaitapu.co.nz/" target="_blank"&gt;The Store&lt;/a&gt; in Tai Tapu to celebrate before tootling home at last. I even convinced them to make me a massive soy milk shake...delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After eating far FAR too much it was time for the final few kilometres to home on familiar ground. The Old Tai Tapu Road is where we ride the Tuesday night Time Trials most nights during the summer and it was kind of fun to be riding it without the pain and suffering we're normally feeling by this stage of the ride!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then all of a sudden we were home. It felt kind of happy and sad at the same time because it had been such an amazing adventure but I had kind of missed our little house too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it too early to start planning our next cycle touring adventure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-hNnfII629gU/VNh5k-x2OGI/AAAAAAAAGPA/BstvyenUJLE/s640/bye%2521.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;And one last bonus photo from our awesome adventure with the big green monster: M waving goodbye to the West Coast. I miss the coast!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/in-which-the-big-green-monster-finally-makes-it-home-part-five/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">126a2ee8-53d7-4e48-9c42-1a579116f848</guid><category>road cycling</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><category>cycle tour 2014/2015</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 09:35:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>In which we bounce along the river bed and get ourselves pretty tired: Part Four</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Omakau, in Central Otago, is a small town partway along the &lt;a href="http://www.otagocentralrailtrail.co.nz/"&gt;Otago Central Rail Trail&lt;/a&gt;. A couple of years we rode the trail with M's sister and some friends, managing to find the only 3 days of freezing cold rain during a long stretch of ridiculously hot weather. This time the sun was most definitely out and we were loving a bit of easy riding and all the friendly people on the trail including these two Aussie ladies with the most awesomely cute &lt;a href="https://www.bikefriday.com/"&gt;Bike Friday&lt;/a&gt; bikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-2Jff8LzZWmY/VNCVklg0iHI/AAAAAAAAGM0/SAr3A4AX0qg/s640/12-day8scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;The Otago Rail Trail with the Poolburn Viaduct (bottom right), one of the tunnels on route (top right) and cool bikes (bottom left).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were only riding the 29km from Omakau to Oturehua before heading off towards the Omarama Saddle but I think it's probably my favourite section, with a cool long tunnel and the Poolburn Viaduct. Plus there is a very cool General Store at Oturehua. After a delicious early lunch we set off in the direction of St Bathans. A few kms before St Bathans is the turn off towards &lt;a href="http://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-visit/otago/central-otago/oteake-conservation-park/"&gt;Oteake Conservation Park&lt;/a&gt;. The gravel road felt like it went on for ages but we finally reached the Homestead campsite where we lazed under a tree eating chips for a while to recuperate a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there we headed up the valley on the &lt;a href="http://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/tracks-and-walks/canterbury/mackenzie-country-and-waitaki/manuherikia-river-tracks/"&gt;West Manukerikia Track&lt;/a&gt;, aiming for Top Hut at the bottom of the Omarama Saddle. The track was pretty good for the first 3km to the junction then got pretty bumpy and rocky with many stream crossings (over 20!) we pushed through. I don't think we could have gotten the tandem through most of them even if we'd tried. The water was super refreshing though as it was pretty hot by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-XMpsiBgZi7U/VNCVlJikOjI/AAAAAAAAGM4/vONODCdnpyY/s640/13-day8scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;A gorgeous day on the West Manukerikia Track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made it to Boundary Creek Hut after about 1 1/2 hours with lots of daylight remaining so continued on the next 8km to Top Hut which took us another 1 1/2 hours. We were both exhausted by this point and super excited to reach the hut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say, this track was definitely pushing the boundaries of what our bike is capable of! Fully laden with no suspension makes riding across all those rocks was pretty rough going! Can we get a dual suspension mountain bike tandem please M?!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-3qMOamYegIM/VNCVlIHtCGI/AAAAAAAAGM8/jp_1gnxL__Y/s640/14-day9scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Left: Top Hut on the West Manukerikia Track. Right: shoe repairs with electrical tape and strapping tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We'd discovered my mountain bike shoes were falling apart so the left one had to be held together with electrical and strapping tapes! They have had a good life though, lasting nearly 8 and a half years, with the last few years definitely being thrashed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, what's the best way to start another day of cycle touring? How about climbing nearly 300 metres in just over 1.5km! Definitely got the lungs working! We did have to push a little bit when we wobbled a bit out of control on the rocky track but otherwise the tandem seemed to be loving it! The descent on the other side however was a bit rough going for our poor brakes, being over 600 metres of steep, rocky gravel. Exhausting! Although a few years ago &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/since_i_ve_been_gone_/"&gt;we rode our mountain bikes up this side&lt;/a&gt; and onto the ridge above the saddle (only to have to turn around due to icy snow on the tops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-2Z18DpsFRZU/VNCVmNxy0BI/AAAAAAAAGNE/L1KTwPDgQXs/s640/15-day9scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Letting the discs cool down (and admiring the awesome scenery) on the descent from Omarama Saddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we arrived at Omarama the heat was getting a bit riduclous and it wasn't even midday yet. We gorged on fresh stone fruit and tried to cool off a bit before setting off onto the &lt;a href="http://www.alps2ocean.com/"&gt;Alps 2 Ocean Cycle Trail&lt;/a&gt; towards Twizel. This is where a lack of reading the notes caused a bit of grief. For some reason I'd managed to mistake the trail distance to Twizel as being only 40km from Omarama but not long after we set off on our way I realised it was actually 80km! You know, just a small difference when it was already 1pm. Now a sensible person would be like, yeah, let's stay at Lake Ohau instead (40km) but sometimes I am far too stubborn for my own good so Twizel it was, no matter what!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were doing the trail backwards from Omarama to Tekapo which meant it was basically heading on it's way up. The trail heads inland towards Lake Ohau via a pretty awesome single track around the base of the Ohau Range with about a 400 metre climb to its highest point (going our direction). Fortunately it's a pretty nice gradient and flows really nicely. But I was still pretty tired by the top. We then had to do some bike maintenance as the front brake pads were wearing pretty thin (VERY thin). We didn't have any spare ones (the list of spare parts we should have had with us was growing by this point!) so M just did a switch which got us down the hill okay but he took things pretty carefully just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-JGtwEOyv97w/VNCXqnRXqZI/AAAAAAAAGNc/MqPJFORyQbw/s640/16-day9scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;A hot day on the Alps 2 Ocean Cycle Trail (so hot that dunking your cycling top in a freezing cold stream was essential to stay sane).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was grumpy and tired by the time we reached Lake Ohau Lodge but a bottle of ginger beer did help a bit. We then headed off along the super whizzy single track around the edge of the lake. It was fantastic, even for someone as tired as me! Then M got into time trial mode for the last 20km along the canal road into Twizel! After a delicious dinner from the local Thai restaurant M was super kind and got us a cabin for the night so I could attempt to recover!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lazy morning then some more bike maintenance (we managed to find one set of brake pads - yay!) we were on our way again, just in time for the heat of the afternoon! Because we were both pretty tired it was a pretty cruisy ride from Twizel to Lake Tekapo via the Alps 2 Ocean Cycle Trail which was mostly on a gravel track around the edge of Lake Pukaki then along the canal road into Tekapo. Despite being a short day my legs (and bottom!) were feeling rather shattered and I was too tired to go for a swim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-I17fvCzbgR0/VNhwTUOevLI/AAAAAAAAGN8/TRs2_Z_WJ3k/s640/17-day10scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Chilling by Lake Pukaki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campsite down by the lake front in Tekapo was so busy we ended up camping amongst the trees right down by the lake which was quite cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-EGSy6XAY2EY/VNhwTX23iEI/AAAAAAAAGN4/Bsjzn0EaQL0/s640/18-day10scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;A bonus picture by M from Tekapo in the evening. Looks a bit spooky!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We'd really put our tandem to the test and somehow it had survived mostly intact but with 4 more days to get back to Christchurch and 2 very tired people (no rest day is a really stupid idea!), it was all beginning to feel a bit too much...&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/in-which-we-bounce-along-the-river-bed-and-get-ourselves-pretty-tired-part-four/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">504e9aad-d3ae-45f3-97b4-753a87dc07a2</guid><category>mountain biking</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><category>cycle tour 2014/2015</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 08:42:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>In which it rains (surprise!) and we climb a few big hills: Part Three</title><description>&lt;p&gt;We awoke the next morning to the delightful sound of thunder and the rain hammering on the roof so I promptly went back to sleep for a bit longer. By the time I awoke the lightning and thunder were so close together I'm pretty sure it was right on top of us. It sure didn't look good for cycling so we started trying to come up with some plans ranging from staying another night in Haast to seeing if it cleared up by the afternoon and just biking 40km down the road to the DOC campground at Pleasant Flat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ZG_rKdVkb6M/VNBz7v1zchI/AAAAAAAAGKM/m6KBR-C0tcg/s500/rain-poem.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Found at the Haast Visitor Centre! Somewhat fitting don't you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come 10am though the rain had eased (eased, not stopped) and there hadn't been thunder and lightning for a good half an hour so we thought, what the hell, let's give this a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road from Haast makes its way inland following the Haast River before you begin the steep climb up to Haast Pass. The mountains drop steeply everywhere you look and the benefit of a bit of rain is that the waterfalls come out to play. Even better is being on a bike where you can see it all in its magestic glory. About half an hour up the road we caught up to a couple of cycle tourists from Austria who were also out enjoying the weather! We were riding a bit faster than them but tended to stop more as we weren't under a tight deadline (they were aiming for Wanaka that night) so spent most of the day with them which was pretty cool, especially huddling under the shelters at Pleasant Flat (along with the sandflies) for lunch! By this point the rain was starting to return in full force and the temperature was definitely not tropical!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-D4MVCgDNxA4/VNCKHvvAXrI/AAAAAAAAGMU/dsb93COp3A8/s640/pleasant-flat.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Hiding from the rain at Pleasant Flat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch we passed through the Gates of Haast and started the climb. It's pretty fortunate we like climbing as this was one pretty big, steep hill. At least there were a couple of waterfalls to visit and rest the legs at. At one point during the climb some guy pulled his car over and jumped into the middle of the road to take photos of us! I imagine to those passing in vehicles it probably looked like a miserable experience, riding a fully laden bike in the pouring rain but actually I was quite enjoying myself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5eGPkdSEt64/VNBz7tXpK1I/AAAAAAAAGKU/IGiC9GRW524/s640/07-day6-1scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;A wet day on the way to Haast Pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made it up to the pass in pretty good time with high hopes that the sun might reach us (you know, having left the West Coast and all that) but it was not to be. In fact, it was a ridiculously cold descent to Makarora where we arrived to find the cafe had no power and therefore no hot drinks (tragic!) but they did have a fire so we sat there for a while trying to defrost before heading off again. We finally pulled into our campsite at Boundary Creek just as the rain was starting to ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-FRmiwSqCruY/VNBz7mZWjJI/AAAAAAAAGKQ/ANCvQoZ_I0M/s640/07-day6scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Camping amongst the trees at Boundary Creek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several days on the road we hadn't really seen many cycle tourists (we defined it as being self-sufficient and carrying all your own gear) until today...where we saw at least 20 others, even another tandem. So basically we came to the conclusion that cycle tourists only come out in the wet weather, especially when it comes to the West Coast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, despite it being New Years Eve we went to bed once the sun went down and slept through the night. We are clearly nanas (I think it's been a while since we've actually had a New Years where we've been awake)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day dawned sunny but cold. We set off along the road only to find that we'd managed to brake a spoke. It had probably happened early the previous day (we had heard a strange sound, like the sound of a twig braking but hadn't seen anything amiss at the time although we didn't check the spokes as it hadn't occurred to us). Not so good. Luckily it wasn't a huge distance to Wanaka (about 50km) but it was New Years so we weren't super optimistic about finding a bike mechanic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a pretty cruisey ride into Wanaka with glorious views of both Lake Wanaka and Lake Hawea but I have to say I was glad to arrive in Wanaka, especially to find not 1 but 2 mechanics on duty at &lt;a href="https://www.torpedo7.co.nz/wanaka"&gt;Racers Edge Torpedo7&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you so much guys for fixing our bike!! They were joking that it was so fancy it was from the future so I think we gave them a little bit of excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hot by the time the bike was finished so it was time for a swim in the lake (cold!) and some lazing in the sun reading my book (a kindle is absolutely brilliant for this kind of trip).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-RxH44K18L4Y/VNCC_1LTojI/AAAAAAAAGKw/AC2VCjYkE2A/s640/08-day6scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanaka is beautiful but in summer it is so ridiculously busy and noisy and really not for people like us who don't like partying or staying up late (makes us sound so old!). We were pretty glad to be leaving and heading towards quiet roads and exciting adventures the next morning. The plan was to head over &lt;a href="http://southernheritage.org.nz/otagotrails/trails/pdf/thomsongorgeroad.pdf"&gt;Thomson Gorge Road&lt;/a&gt; to Omakau. We checked out the Clutha River Trails on the way but after 2 frustrating obstacles (a fence we couldn't get through without removing all our gear and a bridge with steps on either side which also required removing our gear) we bailed and continued along the highway. Once finally onto the gravel roads our mood started to rise and I felt a sense of relief. Wanaka had been so busy that it almost felt like I'd been holding my breath the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-IsvBimlHtg4/VNCFIhYR1GI/AAAAAAAAGLM/FPDAmF8aTQY/s640/09-day7scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;The start of the Thomson Gorge Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomson Gorge Road is a remote high country 4WD road across the Dunstan Mountains with early gold mining and pastoral history. It starts off nice and gently through mostly flat, open farmland but you can see the Dunstan Range rising steeply in front of you. Once it starts climbing your legs soon know about it. Fortunately the views are spectacular and there are a few old batteries to have a look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-GFEwDH4Y6ps/VNCFINw23lI/AAAAAAAAGLI/cNmARPlTLcQ/s640/10-day7scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Parked up by the "Come in Time" Stamper Battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn't too hot for the ascent which was a relief but it was pretty windy up at the saddle and then the sun came out in full force for the descent (which actually has a lot more climb than I expected...like A LOT more!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-X0x6xtiE83o/VNCHijNnb6I/AAAAAAAAGLo/1cz1e1gVEck/s640/11-day7scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Clockwise from top left: "Come in Time" battery, the Thomson Gorge, an old stone hut just after the saddle, chilling at the saddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the descent proper began we had to stop a few times to stop the discs (our tandem has cable disc brakes - they may be super big but we were also fully loaded so that's a lot of force going through the discs to slow us down and keep the bike under control) from overheating too much as it was pretty long and steep. My wrist was ridiculously sore by this stage which was frustrating but it was a fantastic day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-JZfkHR8D2xU/VNCJOLGTyVI/AAAAAAAAGMA/iJ3JSmcWfYQ/s640/12-day7scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been a little apprehensive of how our tandem would handle the Thomson Gorge Road but it ended up being a piece of cake for it (well, apart from the discs overheating a bit but that wasn't very surprising considering just how steep it was). The real test of just what our tandem could handle was yet to come...&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/in-which-it-rains-surprise-and-we-climb-a-few-big-hills-part-three/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61660963-74d1-4ad6-98b3-f4e76c8020aa</guid><category>mountain biking</category><category>road cycling</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><category>cycle tour 2014/2015</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 08:50:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>In which I am seduced by the magic of the West Coast: Part Two</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So I left off with us trapped on the wrong side of the river from Ross (Read &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/in-which-the-big-green-monster-gets-stuck-on-the-wrong-side-of-the-river-part-one/"&gt;part one&lt;/a&gt; of our cycling holiday)...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we were about to turn back we saw a lady crossing the river carrying her dog. She seemed to be making good progress despite the water being waist-deep. We made our way back down to the river bank to meet her and see what it was like. M is vastly more experienced and confident in rivers than me so he helped me across then proceeded to make several trips carrying all our gear and then, finally, the bike which was really quite impressive and I wished I'd taken a photo but at the time I was more concerned about him losing his balance in the current.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once on the other side it was a quick ride into Ross for a walk around some of the historic sites (M has some family history here) before carrying on to the DOC campsite at Lake Ianthe for the night. It's a beautiful spot but, like pretty much everywhere on the West Coast, you are sharing it with an awful lot of sandflies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Q_Ja2uZIRvU/VMXzhoPkdKI/AAAAAAAAGIo/6GaWrdTZzNk/s640/04-01.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;A drizzly morning at Lake Ianthe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning started off pretty drizzly which made packing up a little tricky but it wasn't long before the sun came out in full force. The plan for the day was to ride down the highway to Fox Glacier, stopping at Franz Josef for lunch and supplies. It was pretty tough going after the adventures of the day before and we both were constantly hungry! Consequently it took us a bit longer to get to Franz than my stomach wanted it to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-OcjeF9Nl4Dc/VMXzicRDJUI/AAAAAAAAGIs/6dnPjc1Zb3Y/s640/04-day3scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;After a bit of a grey, drizzly start to the day the sun was out in full force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately just as we were pulling in, so too did the rain so we ended up eating lunch under a bus shelter hoping it would clear up soon. I possibly shouldn't have wished so hard because the last 23km section to Fox Glacier was ridiculously hot and we both managed to get sunburnt! The road between the 2 glaciers is absolutely beautiful though, complete with 3 delightful climbs to test weary legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-6cYes_aO_c0/VMXzkwnFb7I/AAAAAAAAGI4/gOT_Js-Xj_k/s640/05-day3scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Left: Fox Glacier. Right: gear explosion at the Fox Glacier campground!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After pitching our tent at the campground, we took the bike for a spin on the mountain bike track out to the glacier carpark and ran the rest of the way up to the glacier for a look. Good times! I think I fell head over heels in love with Fox Glacier. I want to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning we got up a bit earlier to try and beat the forecasted weather bomb to Haast as we'd booked a cabin the previous day after hearing the weather forecast. We thought we might have to ride the final coastal section in the rain but aimed to get as much of the ride done before it arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were both feeling lots better today and the scenery just got better and better and the traffic less and less. We even managed to score free food and encouragement from the tour guide of a commercial cycling tour making their way down the coast which was pretty cool. We also discovered New Zealand's &lt;a href="http://www.aatravel.co.nz/newsletter/destinatioNZ/2014/oct/most-loved-beaches.php"&gt;8th most loved beach&lt;/a&gt; (apparently), Bruce Bay (just after getting drenched by a typically heavy West Coast 'shower'). I can't say it is a beach I would love to hang out and go swimming at but it sure is spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-3rCLiuRn94M/VMXzlN-7wQI/AAAAAAAAGI8/dSykPDtCQUg/s640/05-brucebay.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Bruce Bay, apparently the 8th most loved NZ beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just can't explain how magic riding down the coast was. I think we both wished we'd had more time to explore more. I did get a bit tired near the end of the climbs around Knights Point but it was awesome. The coast is so wild. We stopped at Ship Creek and wandered around the various tracks through the dunes and bush before continuing along the final stretch of road into Haast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-PwHFpS4LN8M/VMX8LoO2rRI/AAAAAAAAGJk/6Z-FI9Hk11A/s640/06-day4scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;West Coast magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather was so much better than expected with only the downpour (but it was HEAVY!). Once we were safely tucked into our cabin in the evening the rain began...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-LTaZ4EjVvr0/VMX8LxapHuI/AAAAAAAAGJo/1mRnlHcMRaU/s640/07-haast.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="font-style:italic;text-align:center;"&gt;Dangerous times at the Haast Visitor Centre!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/in-which-i-am-seduced-by-the-magic-of-the-west-coast-part-two/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f6770219-d91a-4177-ac22-2401188ac245</guid><category>mountain biking</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><category>cycle tour 2014/2015</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2015 08:38:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>In which the big green monster gets stuck on the wrong side of a river: Part One</title><description>&lt;p&gt;After a bit of mad packing on Christmas night (desperately trying to cram everything in) we set our alarm for an early start the next day. I can't say I was thrilled to hear the alarm go off in the morning but we got ourselves underway, if not a little wobbly, and biked off to the train station for stage one of our adventure: the &lt;a href="http://www.kiwirailscenic.co.nz/tranzalpine/"&gt;Tranz Alpine&lt;/a&gt; train journey from Christchurch to Greymouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-nQvsrDEpriU/VL4b8svTSII/AAAAAAAAGHk/4Ej3bRRLOZQ/s640/01-train.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always wanted to do this train trip and it was seriously cool (well, I do quite like trains!). I loved how you were provided with headphones which gave you commentary on the land and its history as you tootled along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arriving in Greymouth we then wobbled our way to the awesome Global Village Backpackers (definitely the place to stay in Greymouth) where we met an older German couple who were also cycle touring. We had a great time chatting away to them and getting excited about the ride ahead. As we discovered time and time again on this trip, our bike was certainly a talking point and all sorts of people would come up to talk to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-6m-ZrbxXTjo/VL4b9b_K9YI/AAAAAAAAGHs/S_BC6fqsCm4/s640/01-zee-start.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our trip I'd basically linked together a selection of trips from the &lt;a href="http://www.kennett.co.nz/product/classic-new-zealand-cycle-trails/"&gt;Kennett Brothers Classic New Zealand Cycle Trails&lt;/a&gt; book that took us down the West Coast and inland to Wanaka then over a couple of passes and through the Mackenzie Basin then back home again. Day One would see us start the &lt;a href="http://www.westcoastwildernesstrail.co.nz/"&gt;West Coast Wilderness Trail&lt;/a&gt; which would take us to our accommodation for the night in the middle of nowhere, &lt;a href="http://cowboyparadise.co.nz/"&gt;Cowboy Paradise&lt;/a&gt;. A nice easy day of about 70km or so mostly on gravel roads or cycle trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-7OCxfyF3PEc/VL4cAv0GiPI/AAAAAAAAGII/9Rl9Hpv6WlU/s640/03-day1scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a bit overcast but a pretty nice riding temperature and we'd cruised along the coast from Greymouth and made it to Kumara by mid morning. From there the track turned away from the roads, cruising around the Kapitea Reservoir. It was beautiful and super quiet although we met another couple heading the same way as us and another couple heading the other way that we knew. Once we got close to Cowboy Paradise there were these ridiculously tight corners to get down the hill which were mostly definitely not tandem-friendly so we had to push round them (the ones we did ride I was squealing at the back!). We made it to Cowboy Paradise just after 2pm for a nice relaxing afternoon. An awesome and relaxing start to the trip. I should have made the most of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weather bomb was supposed to hit overnight but it didn't really happen as far as I could tell. It rained a bit but nothing too serious (well, for the West Coast which is notorious for rain) and we woke to a light drizzle and thick mist. Exciting! The first part of the trail swooped down off the hillside through beautiful native bush to the river. We then climbed up and over to Lake Kaniere and along the Kaniere Water Race which certainly raised my heartrate. It would be an easy track to ride by yourself but the track is narrow and drops off steeply on one side to the river and to the water race on the other side and on the back of the tandem all I can see are dropoffs! Super beautiful though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-MJroaoNzAKU/VL4b-UFa0DI/AAAAAAAAGH0/seMWgd1BMks/s640/02-day2scenery.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we knew it though we were in Hokitika where we attempted to cram more food into our bags from the supermarket and continued off into the now ridiculously hot and sunny afternoon. All was going so well with a beautiful track that cruised through the bush and a delicious picnic lunch. I should have known it was too good to be true because then came the final coastal section to Ross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew there was a chance this section of the trail was not complete but according to our book it was still rideable except it was a grade 4 instead of a grade 2 so we weren't that surprised to see a sign just before the coastal section saying the track was closed then a sign on the gate saying the road was unmaintained and to enter at your own risk. It all just sounded like a challenge. It started off all fine except for the bridges weren't all rideable so we either walked across them or through the streams. But the track steadily became more covered in gorse and particularly swampy. Pretty tough going for a tandem with no suspension and packed to the brim. But again, nothing we couldn't handle (apart from my wrist becoming pretty sore but that is pretty much expected these days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, with Ross in sight (the end of the trail) we came up to the final bridge across the Totara River...which was under structural repair and missing pretty much all of its floor missing apart from a very narrow plank and rather dodgy looking handrail. Not conducive to crossing with a bike and lots of gear. We tried to follow the side of the river out to the main road but were continuously blocked by endless rough, muddy farmland which seemed to end in scrub and more mud or the river, again. M also tried to see if the river was crossable but on the far side near the bank it became deep and fairly fast flowing. Not something to risk without knowing how deep it was, especially as we'd have to get all our gear and bike over as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-DU87C7pkw7A/VL4cACmZ6cI/AAAAAAAAGIA/VZ1i4ljd78A/s640/04-day1river.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;This photo makes the river look shallow...which it is at this point but on the far side it is much deeper (i.e. you can't see the bottom) and faster flowing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was starting to get pretty late and we were both getting pretty frustrated as it was looking like we'd have to head back along the track again and ride round the road which would take several hours. Things were not looking good...&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/in-which-the-big-green-monster-gets-stuck-on-the-wrong-side-of-the-river-part-one/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">78fa0b65-1dd9-400b-b800-7cf29868115f</guid><category>mountain biking</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><category>cycle tour 2014/2015</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 09:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Christmas is tasty!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;We're back!! After 2 weeks of cycle touring in the South Island we finally made it home on Friday afternoon and are just beginning to surface again. We must be feeling good though as we were out riding again today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, before we left it was Christmas and what is Christmas without a tofukey and christmas pudding right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-niIE2luqGAI/VLHyaZdnPLI/AAAAAAAAGHA/z3eWDR-lKmU/s640/xmas-lunch.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;My plate with tofukey and tahini gravy and lots of delicious vegetables and salads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-AzmjFg5qoLc/VLHybBy9qiI/AAAAAAAAGHI/uGhwqyK2Oc8/s640/xmas-pudding.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;There's nothing quite like a flaming pudding!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-sMZwNi3r6i0/VLHyblVwmwI/AAAAAAAAGHM/5rx-a-VIzg4/s640/xmas-dessert.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Christmas pudding, delicious fresh berries and homemade vegan vanilla ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and a gorgeous tree made by M's mum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-NDGpBkF7l_0/VLHxjSkNsfI/AAAAAAAAGG0/zOO55-aORHU/s640/xmas-tree.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall try and get at least one post up about our cycling trip this week...but you know how these things go. Work may not start until Thursday but I have a dress to make for my cousin's wedding and summer days to have adventures in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. thank M for the glorious blog title :-P&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/christmas-is-tasty/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">76471b3a-96b0-47bc-b172-29755cdc4c46</guid><category>dessert</category><category>food</category><category>baking</category><category>vegan cooking</category><category>life</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 03:56:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghans are tasty</title><description>&lt;p&gt;One more sleep and then it's Christmas! Exciting! And then on Boxing Day we're off on the train to Greymouth then setting off on a bit of a cycling adventure down the West Coast and (hopefully) eventually back to Christchurch. Even more exciting! Although I probably should pack...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since our tandem arrived we've been doing a lot of riding. At the end of October we did our first &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randonneuring"&gt;randonneuring&lt;/a&gt; event with the &lt;a href="https://www.kiwirandonneurs.org.nz/"&gt;Kiwi Randonneurs&lt;/a&gt;, a 400km loop from Greymouth to Greymouth in a day (via Reefton &gt; Springs Junction &gt; Murchison &gt; Westport). Quite possibly also the last time I ever ride that far in one day! I mean, all the beautiful scenery down the West Coast from Westport and it was in the dark! It would make a beautiful two-day ride though. Anyway, we survived and it got me pretty keen for some cycle touring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-lBj5zyYQBbI/VJpZ9Q-ETbI/AAAAAAAAGE8/-9grHFryBA4/s640/greymouth-ride.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;About half an hour into the 400km Greymouth ride. Photo by Shane Davidson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday evenings are normally time trials along Old Tai Tapu Rd with the Canterbury Time Trial Association. It's pretty cool 'cause I definitely wouldn't normally want to ride for 16km along a flat course as fast as I can. That just sounds like torture! We are the only tandem there but there is a trike and it's always fun to see the pro riders with their skin suits, aero helmets and swanky time trial bikes. Some even bring some pretty fancy wind trainers to warm up on first. At the start of December each year there is also the hill climb time trial from the Blue Duck by Motukarara to just past the top of Kennedy's. Perfect conditions this year saw us with a new PB which will be ridiculously difficult to beat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the usual rides we also had a fun day out riding on the Peninsula down to Little Akaloa and round the bays to Okains Bay with the Emilys. EW and I then dragged ourselves round a 6-hour rogaine the following day...you've got to make the most of summery weather when it's here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Ca1Qkib-zBU/VJpegB_oeJI/AAAAAAAAGFY/N78u2wPz55s/s640/biking.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Clockwise from top left: the big green monster chilling at Okains Bay, Little Akaloa - many steep climbs ahead, EW shows us just how steep Okains Bay Road can be, top of Okains Bay Road - yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's been various orienteering events, the Mountain Bike Orienteering Nationals, the Wedding of the Year (!), the Vegetarian Expo (so much delicious food! I love it!), book groups (so many awesome books, so little time) and so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early December was the National Rogaine Champs which was held in the &lt;a href="http://www.topomap.co.nz/NZTopoMap/nz17928/Nevis-Crossing/Otago"&gt;Nevis Valley&lt;/a&gt;. I was racing with EW and it went pretty well apart from a few terrible controls!! I could write more here but I've already written enough and it's on my AP log so if you're interested you can read that &lt;a href="http://attackpoint.org/viewlog.jsp/user_2948/period-7/enddate-2014-12-07"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WQFu-ppbt_Q/VJpYvngW8TI/AAAAAAAAGEI/2fuxAs-dPeI/s640/nationals.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;National Rogaine Champs map - you can almost make out our route if you squint hard enough!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course it wouldn't be Christmas without the annual Christmas Rogaine!! 3 hours of good times blundering around in the bush in the mist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-tvommFJPFmo/VJpYwGHhX7I/AAAAAAAAGEM/k3iK1NdUAUQ/s640/xmas-rogaine.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Christmas Rogaine madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I was intending to head back out that way on my run but I wasn't feeling all that great so instead I ended up looping back from the Kiwi and having a bit of an explore. It was supposed to be sunny but as you can see below, ummm, the sun hadn't quite managed to get itself together so instead it was misty and drizzly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-zAa85XyGRRQ/VJpYxAqz_GI/AAAAAAAAGEg/yShyzwJKZbA/s640/wet-run.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;The Port Hills are awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now back to Christmas. The &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/the_dreaded_tofudabeast/"&gt;tofukey&lt;/a&gt; just recently came out of the oven all ready for tomorrow and last night I found myself cooking yet another batch of cookies. I don't think I've ever cooked so many batches of cookies in such a short space of time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-FQD8dIUQ7eA/VJpYyyr86oI/AAAAAAAAGEk/3JmfoHIrzUQ/s640/tofukey.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;The tofukey in various states of preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-_tM1HNgucm8/VJpYyYiQ1JI/AAAAAAAAGEc/AOfHdeOWz5o/s640/cookies.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Last night's cookies: a couple of New Zealand classics with afghans on the left and peanut brownies on the right (both adapted from the Edmonds Cookbook).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas! Here's hoping the typical Kiwi summer storm doesn't hit whilst we're riding (or is that just too optimistic?! It is the West Coast after all) and the little earthquake we just had is just a lone ranger.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/afghans-are-tasty/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a8870386-fe4c-45af-be09-f800a5fd1231</guid><category>christchurch</category><category>running</category><category>rogaine</category><category>food</category><category>vegan cooking</category><category>life</category><category>road cycling</category><category>adventures</category><category>tandem cycling</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 07:02:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It's beginning to smell a lot like Christmas</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Currently in my little kitchen there is Christmas cake in the oven and Christmas pudding on the stove along with a batch of delicious peanut butter cookies on the bench. It's beginning to smell a lot like Christmas in my kitchen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of food, I never got around to blogging about my American food experiences so you'll have to put up with it now. It was a bit of a mixed bag to be honest. I went in with high hopes and they were dashed pretty quickly when we couldn't find bread that tasted, well, anything like the bread we know and love here. It was hard enough trying to find bread without dairy in it and when we did it had a weird texture and tasted sweet. Ugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Boulder M and I did a lot of our shopping at &lt;a href="http://www.alfalfas.com/"&gt;Alfalfa's&lt;/a&gt; as it was close to where we were staying (Chautauqua which was amazing as we were right at the start of the trails leading up into the Flatirons - although an hour and a half run in the hot sun the morning after we arrived might have been a bit much for my jetlagged body!). The variety was pretty cool but it did make me appreciate what we have at home. I really wanted to be a fan but couldn't.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had more luck at restaurants and cafes though. One lunch I got a takeaway reuben sandwich (it sounded very American - I've never seen anything like it on a menu in NZ) from &lt;a href="http://leafvegetarianrestaurant.com/"&gt;Leaf&lt;/a&gt; which was pretty good. Different, but good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GP7RC-_j9WE/VJeZuljjWsI/AAAAAAAAGAE/Bf3r3KeK4MU/s640/food-01.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out Wholefoods in a few places...they are so huge it was a bit frightening but the salad bar things are pretty cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-zRP54PHGH48/VJeZygO1wuI/AAAAAAAAGAc/b9_QSfKbp-w/s640/food-wholefoods.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a pretty impressive range of vegan frozen desserts in these type of places, of which we tried a couple...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-9tvDvBOv7wU/VJeZzZm1ZoI/AAAAAAAAGAk/fBSzioQn1eU/s640/food-freezer.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in Salt Lake City we attempted to visit every vegan eatery in town (well, all the ones that were open during our stay). First up was the &lt;a href="http://verticaldiner.com/"&gt;Vertical Diner&lt;/a&gt;. After spending far too much at REI (not for the first or the last time on our trip!) A then took us there for lunch. I loved this place from the moment we walked in. The menu is fun and the food was super yummy. I wished we could have gone back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-pHi13T00DwA/VJeaNS-PqNI/AAAAAAAAGAw/lqzI4oeRqH8/s640/food-verticaldiner-01.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Clockwise from top left: a burger but I can't remember which one, Jerk Chicken Burrito and another burger of some description!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dessert was definitely a must (hey, we had to try as much food as possible!)...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ekX_WU4IiU4/VJeaOfOF-gI/AAAAAAAAGA0/VTlp6QH09ng/s640/food-verticaldiner-02.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;A banana split sundae and a strawberry brownie sundae - delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up was the &lt;a href="http://www.citycakescafe.com/"&gt;City Cakes Cafe&lt;/a&gt; for lunch whilst exploring Salt Lake City on our own. This place looks like it provides a lot of the vegan cabinet food we saw in other cafes and Wholefoods in the area. The lemon bar was delicious but I wasn't a fan of the more lunch-type food we ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-79ZannT5G9A/VJeaiDF56bI/AAAAAAAAGA8/J-pssegVkB0/s640/food-saltlakecity.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Clockwise from top left: a lemon bar, Mac n' Chezah and a Black Bean Burger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One evening M and I headed into town to &lt;a href="http://www.sagescafe.com/"&gt;Sage's Cafe&lt;/a&gt; a more fancy dinner. M ordered the mushroom stroganoff and I ordered the raw cashew pad thai and we agreed they were both exceptional. Plus the service, from memory, was excellent. If you find yourself in Salt Lake City I would really recommend Sage's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-KuQP-yrsoww/VJearcFzZ5I/AAAAAAAAGBY/tMsGB4UR-ks/s640/food-restaurant.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, dessert was essential...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-4lZxBXMMhL8/VJeasXkWxyI/AAAAAAAAGBc/lMGoYO6cmZ8/s640/food-restaurant-dessert.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Chocolate Chip Cookie Ice Cream Madness and the Tiramisu. Definitely worth it,especially the tiramisu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final cafe I checked out was the &lt;a href="http://www.frischeats.com/"&gt;Frisch Compassionate Eatery&lt;/a&gt; where I got the special of the day which was some kind of spicy 'chicken' nacho dish and the most giant cookie I have ever seen in my life! The nachos were pretty good but I think I would have preferred plain beans to the mock chicken and by the time I came to eat the cookie I think I was over sweet food. The menu here looked pretty awesome though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-V1N7Db6eWlw/VJeg1ea1s0I/AAAAAAAAGCA/vMiiEIqcldE/s640/food-nachos.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You couldn't really go wrong with Mexican though, even in the City Creek Mall. And corn chips here are so much more delicious than most we can buy at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-tw1r4NrDIxg/VJeaoOiTDTI/AAAAAAAAGBE/XG55jkk8WMc/s640/food-mexican.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole though we did most of our own cooking. After Boulder we camped in Leadville for some altitude training before the &lt;a href="http://blog.katiebolt.com/mountain-lions-and-fallen-logs/"&gt;rogaine&lt;/a&gt; (when you live at sea level it's a bit of an adjustment!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-lNo3YaisONk/VJeZvieiK5I/AAAAAAAAGAM/19eUZTTgAQA/s640/food-02.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first morning we cooked up some terribly awful pancakes made from some boxed mix we found at a supermarket. They may have looked all fluffy but they tasted pretty awful! But the boys did try their hand at flipping them much to our entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-y_DlC0F30I0/VJentRt932I/AAAAAAAAGCY/C356cQNGjlE/s640/leadville.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Camping by Turquoise Lake was beautiful with the added bonus of a track going right past our tent for an easy morning run...followed by a swim in the lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in Salt Lake City we made pizza once my parents arrived and I got to try out some vegan cheese. It sort of melted but not like some of the pictures I'd seen and it kind of tasted a little bit plasticy (am I being too fussy here? Give me some of the European or British vegan cheeses any day...I don't care if they don't melt). The pizza was delicious though despite the cheese and the weird mock bacon we tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OQZ0b0IPC1M/VJeap9GSwtI/AAAAAAAAGBM/SWGjHmJ9uaI/s640/food-pizza.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best food of the whole trip though was definitely all the fresh summer berries, especially when out adventuring...or lazing in the sun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-6Uiybjvk8Fw/VJevif8ieyI/AAAAAAAAGDE/9XKGuuP4gKE/s640/mtbing.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Mountain biking in the hills above Park City. Perfect riding for me as it started with a big long climb up to the top (and then a punnet of raspberries of course!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-3ZCAzUJPb0o/VJevi3DbfzI/AAAAAAAAGDI/ET1s9IqVo34/s640/wolverine.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;Exploring Mt Wolverine in the rain then meeting my parents and R checking out all the lakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-gqW8Qls3LTI/VJew1mH_e6I/AAAAAAAAGDc/6PweDz3wIYU/s640/140901_123851.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic;"&gt;And the best bit? Lazing around by a lake after eating far too many berries (if that is actually possible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, no more USA trip posts now. I think I'm done (and now hopelessly behind on everything since then!).&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://blog.katiebolt.com/its-beginning-to-smell-a-lot-like-christmas/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f286f93f-affa-4c4f-a196-39c247e2965b</guid><category>dessert</category><category>food</category><category>raw food</category><category>vegan cooking</category><category>mountain biking</category><category>adventures</category><category>usa 2014</category><dc:creator>Katie</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 05:54:28 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>